<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>By the King a proclamation to restraine the kings subiects from departing out of the realme without licence.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1625-1649 : Charles I)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1635</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A22588</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 9037</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S123784</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">33150563</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 33150563</idno>
            <idno type="VID">28659</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A22588)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 28659)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1877:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>By the King a proclamation to restraine the kings subiects from departing out of the realme without licence.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1625-1649 : Charles I)</author>
                  <author>Charles I, King of England, 1600-1649.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Robert Barker, Printer to the Kings most Excellent Maiestie: And by the Assignes of Iohn Bill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1635.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Requiring permission to travel from king or privy council.</note>
                  <note>"Giuen at Our Court at Oatelands, the one and twentieth day of Iuly in the eleuenth yeare of Our Reigne."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Society of Antiquaries.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Passports --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1625-1649.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  London (England) --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="royal_proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:28659:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 16 -->
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <head>C R</head>
                  <q>DIEV ET MON DROIT</q>
                  <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> By the King.</head>
            <head type="sub">¶ A Proclamation to reſtraine the Kings Subiects from departing out of the Realme without licence.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas it is one of the principall duties of all Our Subiects, to attend</hi> at all times the ſeruice and defence of their King and natiue Countrey, either within the Realme, or without, when they ſhall be thereunto re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired: And foreſeeing in Our Princely prouidence what danger might enſue to this State, if Our Subiects might at their pleaſure paſſe and depart out of this Realme, into the Kingdomes, Countreys, and Dominions of forraine Kings or States: For preuention whereof, We haue thought fit to publiſh Our Royall wil and commandement in that behalfe; And doe therefore hereby, ſtraitly prohibite and forbid all Our Subiects of this Our Realme, or of any of the Dominions of the ſame, of what eſtate or degree ſoeuer they be, that they or any of them (other then Souldiers, Mariners, Merchants, and their Factors, and Apprentices) ſhall not at any time hereafter, without the ſpeciall licence of Vs, or of ſix, or more of Our Priuie Councill, vnder their hands (whereof one of Our principall Secretaries to be one) paſſe or depart out of this Our Realme of England, or any of the Dominions thereof, into the Kingdomes, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys, Territories, or Dominions of any forraine King, Prince, State, or Potentate, vpon ſuch cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, and other great and heauie paines and penalties, as by the Lawes or Statures of this Realme may be inflicted vpon them. And We doe hereby alſo require and command all Our Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and Miniſters in Our ſeuerall Ports of this Realme; that hereafter they ſuffer none of our ſaid Subiects to paſſe without ſuch licence; And that no Owners, Maſters, or Mariners of any ſhips or veſſels, doe from henceforth carry, or tranſport beyond the Seas, any perſon or perſons whatſoeuer, without ſuch licence ſo obtained from Vs, or ſuch ſix, or more of Our Priuy Councill; and the ſame firſt ſhewed, and duely entred with the Officer of the Port, from whence ſuch perſon is to paſſe, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on paine of Our high diſpleaſure, and ſuch forfeitures, and loſſe of Office, ſhip or veſſell, and other penalties, as by the Lawes and Statues of this Our Realme are ordained and prouided in that behalfe. Prouided alwayes, that if any ſuch Souldiers, Mariners, Merchants, or their Factors and Apprentices, as are herein excepted and permitted to paſſe without licence, doe after their depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture out of this Realme, commit, attempt, or aſſent to any act, deuice, plot, or thing againſt Vs, or any Our Kingdomes or Dominions, or againſt any of Our Lawes or Statutes: That euery ſuch perſon ſo offending, ſhall loſe the benefit of the ſaid exception, and ſhall to all intents and purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes be taken and adiudged to be, as one that maliciouſly and contemptuouſly paſſeth or departeth out of this Realme contrary to the tenour and effect of theſe preſents.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given at Our Court at Oatelands <date>the one and twentieth day of Iuly in the eleventh yeare of Our Reigne.</date>
               </dateline>
               <lb/>
God ſaue the King.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Imprinted at London by ROBERT BARKER, Printer to the Kings moſt Excellent Maieſtie: And by the Aſsignes of Iohn Bill. 1635.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
